GIACOMO ROSILHO DE SOUZA

Applied Mathematician (PhD) | Researcher | Simulation Engineer

+41 79 485 40 27 • giacomo.rosilhodesouza@gmail.com • grosilho.ch • Lugano, Switzerland • Swiss and Brazilian

Summary

Applied mathematician expert in **physic-based simulations**, **numerical methods**, **mathematical models**, **stochastic processes**, and **optimization**. Model-based design of numerical strategies. Implement and test algorithms in **Python**, **C++**, and **MATLAB**. Exceptional **communication** skills acquired through presenting at international conferences and collaborations. Independent researcher. Author of several papers in top-tier journals, <u>full list</u>.

Selected Achievements

C++ Multi-scale Stochastic Differential Equations

Designed and implemented fast **Monte Carlo** integration methods achieving speedup factors of 10.

C++ Discontinuous Finite Elements

Optimized nonlinear **finite element** simulation code, achieving speed-up of 5.

Python Parallel computing

Developed and implemented the first parallel-in-time solver. Tested accuracy and stability on HPC machines on over 1000 processors.

Skills

Simulation Engineering:

Numerical methods · Numerical integration · Runge-Kutta methods · Exponential methods · Finite elements · Finite differences · Stabilization methods · Numerical linear algebra · High-performance computing · Boundary element methods · Parallel computing · Nonlinear multi-grid methods · Large-scale simulations · Mixed-precision methods · Tau-leap methods · Monte Carlo simulations · Optimization methods · Spectral deferred corrections

Mathematics:

Dynamic Systems · Differential equations · Calculus · Linear Algebra · Stochastic Calculus · Optimization · Probability · Statistics

 $\textbf{Software Engineering:} \ \ \textbf{Python} \cdot \textbf{C++} \cdot \textbf{MATLAB} \cdot \textbf{Git} \cdot \textbf{CMake} \cdot \textbf{Linux/Unix} \cdot \textbf{Docker} \cdot \textbf{Conda}$

Data Analysis and libraries: Pandas · SQL · NumPy · Seaborn · Matplotlib · Scikit-learn · Dash · Machine learning · JAX · Flax

Managerial: Public speaking · Led report writing · Scientific writing · LaTeX · Supervision of talents · Communication

Experience

USI - Università della Svizzera italiana Simulation Engineer

Lugano, Switzerland 11/2021 - 12/2024

- · Contributed to 2 European high-performance computing (HPC) projects. Collaborated with remote teams.
- Developed parallel and multi-scale solvers for large complex systems of nonlinear PDEs, reducing computational time by 50% on 1000 processors (Python).
- · Research on stabilized optimization methods (Python).
- Code optimization for numerical solvers (Python/C++).
- Lecturer, rated 9/10 by MSc students. Supervisor for 3 MSc thesis students.

EPFL - Swiss Federal Technology Institute of Lausanne Research Scientist

Lausanne, Switzerland 06/2020 - 08/2021

- Research in **stochastic** differential equations and **mixed-precision** methods for GPUs, improving computational efficiency by 75% (C++).
- · Lecturer for the MSc course "Numerical integration of dynamical systems".

PhD Student 09/2015 - 05/2020

- Enhanced stochastic differential equations solvers and finite element methods, achieving speed-up factors of 10 (C++).
- Supervisor for 5 BSc and MSc students in research projects.

CSCS - Swiss National Supercomputing Centre

Computational scientist intern

Lugano, Switzerland 09/2013 - 01/2014

Migrated an astrophysics simulation code from CPUs to GPUs (Fortran).

- Code optimization, algorithms, and data structures, achieving a 10x speed-up.
- · Results presented at international conferences.

Selected Publication

Submitted SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing — doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2405.19994

High-order parallel-in-time method for the monodomain equation in cardiac electrophysiology

Parallel-in-time method inspired from iterative numerical linear algebra techniques such as multigrid methods and the nonlinear full approximation scheme (FAS).

Certifications

IBM Data Science Professional Certificate

— data analysis, data cleaning, data visualization, dashboards, supervised/unsupervised machine learning, data science libraries.

Education

EPFL

PhD in Applied Mathematics 09/2015 - 05/2020

09/2012 - 06/2014 MSc in Mathematical Engineering | GPA: 5.75 / 6

EPFL

BSc in Mathematics | GPA: 5.45 / 6 09/2009 - 06/2012

Honors and Awards

Prize in Numerical Analysis

Received international Butcher Prize for excellent communication skills and research quality.

Teaching award at EPFL, 2 times

Prize for excellent quality and commitment in teaching, for detailed course material and delivering clear lectures to students.

Languages

English Fluent French Fluent Italian Native

Spanish Fluent Portuguese Native

Interests

Fermentation

Soy sauce, miso, beer, cheese, kefir, tempeh, kvass,

DIY

Building furniture for home, forging, gardening.

Find me online

in LinkedIn

linkedin.com/in/grosilho

Personal website grosilho.ch

GitHub

github.com/grosilho

Google Scholar

scholar.google.com/citations? user=88Aul6QAAAAJ&hl=en&oi=ao